welcome back to am Northwest here now
with a collection of Alaskan and Inuit art
along with important information about
Ivory we welcome back antique appraiser
Gary gmer great to see you thanks for
having me back you always bring the most
interesting collection so this comes from
one estate right this came up from one
estate out of Bandon Oregon some folks
are downsizing and they and this is just
a part of what they've sent me to deal
with but and so it's been kind of a head
plunge into learning a lot about learn
the history about these things right you
do and kind of and then you learn who
different about different artists and what
not the um the native arts and this is
all Inuit art which you know the Inuits
you think of northern Alaska but actually
it's all around the arctic circle
around the Canada and Greenland are all
kind of related and so the art is all
kind of related um wow there and so a
lot of this is is actually from Canada as
well as Alaska let's talk about let's
talk about the wood carvings first well
that's probably what we think of the
most when we think of the people is wood
carving totem poles and that sort of
thing which was religious um ceremony and
and there has been a big uh push with
the government in in Canada and with the
US to support the Revival of the Native
arts and I brought these along because
as we they all have different symbols
the the birds and whatnot have um
spiritual symbols sure but wood
is just only one of the the of the
mediums that they use and um the um
uh we have a bunch of different rocks
and different things here they they
would use uh seal skin let me ask you how
much would something like this well
they're really cool just a nice small piece
and it's a good artist but not necessarily
the top artist a good artist it's
probably about $150 okay and then and
then this with the seal skin the seal skin
doll this is something that's kind of
interesting because it wasn't native it
wasn't an I that was really native to
their people and so it was kind of made
native dolls to be sold to the market
all of this was made up to be sold to the
white people and the people to the South
I see initially they would have little
carvings like these that were uh the
little carvings that would be like fetishes
and they had a religious symbols way
back 200 years ago okay by the 1850s the
white people had came and started
trading they didn't want to trade their
spiritual pieces sure so they started
carving what they wanted and so a lot of
them were made like these down here the
let's take a look at these tell me those
fun those are done out of a type of Jasper
which is a natural stone up in Alaska
and uh their their emphasis is of course
on the nature that's around them sure
and so again any of these pieces will
range in value from maybe $500 $50
to $500 depending on the artist and
depending on how well carved it is okay but
done like in a Jasper um
and and then this is um
this walrus he's he's great he's a
musox oh musox okay sorry not a walrus
I was thinking of the the Tusk of a
walus so what what is this what is this
material it's called well the the the
official name of it is serpentinite okay
which is but they call it Jade they call
it an they call it Canadian or Alaskan
or Inuit Jade yeah and it's a hard
Stone it's not as hard as soap stones
but it's I mean it's harder than soap
stones but it's easier to carve the people
people and the natives even though they
have access now to any power tools they
would want they still basically refuse
to use them except for cutting maybe a
large block down and they use all the
old tools that they always used to use
yeah that's what and this one you say
would cost would he's about a $500 piece
yeah maybe 500 $600 he has a lot of
work done he has um um Ivory added
to him and what not like that or like
the little birds are sitting on an antler
tell me about these guys aren't they
don't they have personality these two
yeah these here and the the the walrus
and the little tiny walruses in front
shows that the how they could carve um
antlers oh that's these are all Caribou
antlers they would have been made and
so it would been less expensive they
didn't need to you know an easier to carve
but also you're already looking for a
piece that gives you that kind of a
feeling of what movement a movement looks
like speaking of wall ruses
yeah the ancient Walrus
The People's change before contact there
were people that they don't know a lot
about that would carve but they would
carve the the skeleton outside this is
a don't worry about that this is a this
is a car this is a copy of one this is a
modern piece but they would actually
carve the the the um the skeleton of
the creature on the outside and they
think it had kind of a spiritual
significance they're still studying to
find out exactly what it probably meant
but the people that those people had died
out a couple thousand years ago these
now is this Ivory here these are ivory
the ones in the front our little our
little kayaker and and all this little
guy yeah and and the whale that's in
front they're all those are all and
it's walrus Ivory okay can't take you
anywhere I know right okay they're
walrus Ivory and this is one thing I get
probably one of the top questions I
get is about Ivory because we know that
Ivory is banned or so restricted
but that is mainly elephant Ivory
when you hear about the ant and so so uh
elephant Ivory this is walrus Ivory and
one of the ways you tell of course is
the subject helps sure if it's if it's if
it's Inuit it's probably you know from
their walrus test or something like that
but and the Asian is going to be more
um um elephant Ivory and the Elephant
Ivory and I have a I have I don't know
if this can show on camera or not this so
this is an example he Chinese or excuse
me Japanese but on the cut part of the
tooth if you're looking at it it'll have
a cross grein it looks like it's been
cut with a slow saw and that's
how the tooth grows ele or walr iy
grows a little bit different it does not
have that pronounced grain it's one of
the ways you can test it to see
there's no restriction on that
um to to buy and sell the ivory there
walrus Ivory except in the raw form you
can't sell it w incredible pieces Gary
soap stone yeah amazing thank you so much
I appreciate your wealth of information